Hello everyone, welcome to this video.
In this video, we will be discussing two
most important concept. First, we will
begin with the tracing. Then we will
discuss about the metal bar. For any
application, tracing or observability
plays a very crucial role. Especially in
AI, there are quite a few things that
you want to understand or observe.
Right? In the context of a agent, there
are four things that we will observe.
First we will be observing the overall
performance. So here we will say like
you know how muchever seconds how you
know it took to complete the overall
execution.
Then we will you know come to the cost
part where like we will see how many
tokens are used. Then we will see uh how
exactly the execution happened like step
by step. So if at all you wanted to see
like you know what has happened uh you
know throughout the execution you should
be able to observe that. Then using this
you can also do additional uh debugging
right for instance a function it's a
called with a specific value. So you
wanted to trace all this information so
that you can backtrack. So in summary
observability
let you understand why it's set how fast
it set and how much it costed. Right now
let's go to the visual studio code and
see how do we implement this. So this is
how we implement the observability.
So before we try to understand the
implementation let's go up a bit here.
So the Azure E framework uses something
called open telemetry. So that exposes
the span. So span if you try to
understand the span it will be something
of this sort. If you see here it has a
trace ID and the span ID. So the
difference between the trace ID and the
span ID. trace ID it's unique for the
execution wherein the span ID it's
specific within that sub execution say
like you are asking hey what is the
weather in Tokyo so you will have one
trace ID for the entire execution
wherein like the span ID lm LLM
execution will have its own span ID and
like the function calling will be having
its own span ID so think of this way you
sending a corer the corer has a trace ID
the corer number and like the corer goes
to different locations So each location
has the you know location ID fan ID it's
something close to that location ID and
on top of that you will have the you
know location name uh when it received
when it you know move forward uh how
long it waited in that particular
location status whatever is that it has
all this information right so basically
now what we have to do is that we have
to enable the application to uh you know
uh send the trace
uh and like when it sends out the trees
we need we should be able to collect the
trees and you know store the trees in a
format that we we are interested in. So
that's what we are saying here. So we
are saying like hey start the
observability. So basically like you
know shoot out the trace and like
somebody needs to catch so that is where
where like we are using this collector.
So if you look into to this collector
implementation import the span exporter
and like it has couple of methods that
you need to uh extend to. So basically
like now you know the structure and like
using these specific implementation you
should be able to extract the
information from a trees and you should
be able to store the information as the
way you wanted to have it. Right? So uh
otherwise the code will be pretty same.
So like here like I have couple of
functions get weather calculate you know
search or whatever is that. So now
that's like you don't have to do
anything else apart from these three
four lines right so like here like I uh
you know started the trace and like I
mentioned that hey like you have to use
this trace provider uh trace provider
will have two different components. one
is the trace resource other one is the
trace collector uh basically the
telemetry collector right so here like
I'm using a batch span processor so
instead of sending each and every span
I'm you know I will be sending the spans
uh as a batch to this particular
collector now the collector will get all
the span information and then like you
know whatever I have configured to do
like in my case like I will be writing
all the logs into the text file it can
be a text file It can be a database or
it can be anything. You should be able
to send the data to the you know trace
exporter. From a trace exporter, you
should be able to
you know send the data to wherever you
want to have in a format that you wanted
to have it. Right? That's it. Now let me
go ahead and uh run it.
Now let me go ahead and run this. So now
the question I will be asking here what
is the weather for Paris? Right? So now
let me go ahead and ask. So if you think
of this one, right? So first I'm sending
a question to the LLM. I'm asking what
is the weather for Paris. Now LLM will
be getting this input and like it will
will get to know that hey like I need to
call a weather tool for a city called
Paris and then like it will make a call
to the tool that is iteration 2 and the
function will return the respond back to
the LLM. LM will receive that
information and this is going to be the
second input to the LLM. Right now it is
going to finalize the final outcome that
is iteration number three and like uh it
is going to print the result. Right? So
there are four steps we are going to
perform the initial input and like
function call function called results
will be sent back to the llm. Now llm
needs to finalize that and like finally
we will be printing all this
information. So now if you see here this
is how it is going to generate a log
file for me. So as you see here first it
started with the uh GPT mini. So the
this is my initial costing. So for which
it spend about 4
4,600 milliseconds. Then second uh
iteration it made a call to the tool
with all this uh information means if at
all you wanted to even capture further
information you should be able to do
that using the uh span exporter. Now the
LLM will receive the uh response from
the function. It needs to make a or
finalize the final uh outcome. Now
finally we will be printing the uh
telemetry bot in the sense like it is
the outmost wrapper. So it is just going
to print all the uh data for me here. So
it says that the overall execution took
about 7,000 milliseconds right and you
know these many input tokens are the
output tokens are used all those
information now I have the complete
information right so I I I will get to
know that hey like initially like the
user query uh llm received the user
query then made a call to the function
get weather function though I have
couple of functions it made a call to
this particular function now llm
received that input from the function.
Finally, it uh responded back to the
user and uh this is this is how much
time it spent. This is how much token it
has used all those information. Now
using this data like this log I will get
to know the complete execution right so
that is the beauty of this
observability. Now let's go and talk
about uh another uh most important topic
called middleware. So before we try to
go into the implementation now let's try
to understand what is this middleware
it's all about. So remember like with
the observability we are able to
understand the complete program
execution. However like we won't be able
to control the overall execution.
With middleware you should be able to
control the execution as well.
Middleares are also known as
interceptors. So there are four
interceptor
timing interceptor security and function
and token cost. Coming from a net or a
java background middlewarees are nothing
new to you. Let me try to explain. So
let's assume that user is providing a
input. First it will go to the timing
middleware. In my case I'm just starting
the clock. However like you can do
whatever you want to do. Then it it will
go to the security middleware where like
I will be checking the contact safety.
Then it will go to the chat middleware
basically like before the you know user
input submit to the LLM it will go to
the chat middleware where like you can
you know try to reduce the token right
so user is saying some providing some
input you really don't have to submit as
it is you can try to reduce to to
minimize the token right so that is what
you can do it in the uh chat middleware
then you will submit the uh refined
query to the llm lm will see if it needs
to uh execute a function So at this
point in time the first execution first
iteration kind of a done. So at the time
like it will go back and tell the chat
middleware that hey like my execution
first execution it's done. Then at the
time you can print hey like you know in
the first iteration the llm consumed
these many input token these many output
tokens then it will make a function
call. So in the function when you make a
function call the function middleware
get triggered. You can you know extract
the information like what is the
function name what are all the
parameters are passed all those
information and if for all you wanted to
modify something you can very well do so
and then like you can make a call to the
function and the results will be passed
to the llm now this is going to be
iteration two right so before it again
goes to the execution it will again call
the input the chart middleware where
like again you you will you know capture
all this information like a token and
try to reduce the overall
you know input content right uh finally
the LM execution will get finished then
it will again go to the security
middleware and the timing middleware
only one caveat with this approach is
that whenever you use a sync operation
so let's say like most of the scenarios
we will be using async right we will not
be using the just the run method rather
like we will be using a sync run stream
so in that case the Timing middleware
will get called, security middleware get
called and like this chart middleware
even before you know it come to the
execution these two middlewares will get
executed like you know the overall
execution cycle will be completed for
the timing and the security middleware
right the reason is that rest of these
will be asynchronous. So that is in such
a case uh you cannot expect the flow one
after another rather like a timing and
the security will get finished then rest
of the flow will continue like chart
middleware and the function middleware
will get invoked depends on the need
right uh but the like end of the
execution you will not see the timing
middleware and the security middleware
it will get completed in the very
beginning itself
right so now let's see like let's try to
uh simulate this first I'm saying like
uh tell me a simple tell me a joke it's
you know pretty simple chat right first
we will trigger the you know timing
middleware then the security middleware
then LLM right so before go to the LLM
the chart middleware get called the LLM
execution will happen once the after the
execution the again the chart middleware
will get called uh then finally we will
have the result and finally we we are
expected to have a timing middleware so
the uh in in case of a async you will
not see the timing middleware at the
end. The reason is that in this entire
portion it's going to be a sync. So the
control will leave from the main thread
to the subordinate thread. So you in
that sense like the main thread
execution it's already kind of a
completed. So now again let let's try to
see in case of a tool the timing
middleware get called a security
middleware then the LLM middleware or a
chart middleware that will function
middleware get called where like we will
be capturing some of these information
so remember like as a demo I'm just
capturing this information however like
it has the capacity to do anything that
you wanted to do right you can change or
you can control the input or whatever
you want to So you can very well do that
and the security block. So in this case
like what is my password I'm just
saying. So the middle security
middleware detects that this is not
allowed in that sense like it will just
you know come out of the overall
execution. Right now let me go to the
visual studio code. Mware implementation
involves three different portions. First
you need to import the relevant classes.
In this case, I have uh imported the
agent run context, a function invocation
context and the chart context. The
timing and the security will be using
the agent run context and the function
uh middleware will be using function
invocation and the LLM middleware will
be using the chart context that you need
to define the middleware. I will come
back in a moment. So if you see here, I
have defined all these middlewarees
here. all these four middlewarees then
you need to reference those middle words
in the agent definition. So if you see
here apart from the regular instruction
and the tools I have also included all
four middle words here. Now let's go to
the implementation here. Implementation
it's a pretty straightforward. If you
just see uh the timing middleware, it
takes the agent run context and uh you
know it uh starts the timer and print
some information and calls the next
middleware right. So next middleware
will be the security middleware. So if
you just go here, it also takes the
agent run context and if you just come
over here, it checks all the messages
and especially looks for these
particular keywords. If there are any
keywords matches in that message then it
is going to say that the context will be
terminated. The execution will not be
continued otherwise the execution will
continue. As this is just a demo like
this is I kept it very simple but then
like in terms of enterprise application
you will be using the content safety uh
service. Then we have the token counter
or the uh LLM middleware or a chart
middleware. So if you just see here it
uh prints the uh input uh tokens and
like at the end it also prints the
output token. So what you can do is that
instead of just printing the token
estimated token what you can do is that
you can somehow reduce the uh input
right so you know just removing the
unwanted tokens you can remove all of
those just pass the relevant information
to the LLM that way like you can
definitely reduce the overall input
token as well as you can also reduce try
to reduce the output token that is
something that we can do then we will
have a function middleware it takes the
function invocation context it prints
all this information right so you see if
you want to extend some additional if
you want to pass some additional
information you can variable do it
through this middleware so that's about
the definition and uh we discuss about
the registration as well so now let's go
and try to run the uh python program
here so let me go ahead and run the
program let me maximize this so I have
provided some uh predefined find a
prompt here. So let me copy this. So the
first one it will be calling the using
the timing and the token counter. Right?
So just goes here. It says that it
started the middleware sec middleware
also called there is nothing. So there
is no sensitive and it passed. Then it
called the uh you know the input it's
sent to the LLM. Uh before the LLM
executes the chart middleware gets
called and we see the result. So if you
see here the timing middleware and the
security middleware it's completed even
before the chart middleware gets called
right. The reason is that we are using
uh run stream here. So if I just come
over here we are not using the uh
synchronous execution rather this is a
synchronous execution.
So if I just come over here uh here we
are using the asynchronous. So the main
thread will not be waiting and that's
why like uh you know this gets completed
even before uh the actual program
completes right you can very well tweak
this I'm not going to spend a lot of
time here so now let's move forward and
try to uh provide a next prompt here so
now let's say like what is the weather
in Tokyo so in which case it is going to
make a call so first the user question
and like the function LLM will decide it
needs to make a function and it makes a
function call and finally prints the
result. Right? So now let me uh provide
the input here. So the timing model
started security middleware started
timing middleware computed uh chart
middleware started. It founds that it
needs to uh send a message uh to the
function. So you see here now the
function gets called the function
middleware gets uh invoked and then like
finally the chart middleware gets
called. The reason is that the function
returns this value and then the same
value will be passed to the LLM. The LLM
will be finalizing the final outcome. So
that is what you see here. So that is
how it works. Now let me also provide
one more uh prompt here. So now let's
also try the calculator here. So in this
case again so if you see here uh timing
middleware was started and then it it
says that uh it needs to call the get
time and calculate two functions get
called and you see all of these
information. So whatever it's passed all
of these you can find it from the logs
here. Now let's also try to pass some
security rel related
uh query here. So okay now say like what
is my password right? So now if I see
this uh so it is just going to uh it
goes to the security middleware security
middleware block the execution. Now we
are done with the uh that particular
request right now let's see what do we
have so what uh search for user and get
the weather. So this is again going to
be all four middleware. So search for
users.
Uh so first the timing middleware again
security middleware then it uh calls the
functional middleware to search for the
data uh database and get the weather
information. So that's how you can use
the middleware uh just not to capture
the information but also control the
overall execution. So now in this video
we discussed the most important two
topics uh observability and middleware.
Now in the next video we will be
discussing about MCP that is going to be
a lot more interesting.